Hey, hey, what's up, my friend? So,
you've likely been taught to buy stocks
that are going up. After all, you know,
you want to be trading with the trend,
ride the trend, and then sell it at a
higher price.
But, here's the thing. Some of the best
trading opportunities don't come from
buying
stocks that are going up. In fact, it's
buying stocks that are actually falling,
falling in price.
Now, before you think I'm crazy
and I've lost my marbles, right, hear me
out.
Because in this video, I'm going to show
you one of the simplest and most
misunderstood strategies that
professional traders use to profit when
the stocks crash temporarily. It's what
we call mean reversion trading.
Okay, first thing first, what exactly is
mean reversion trading about? So,
markets, they don't move up in one
straight line. Instead, they go up,
makes a pullback, and then goes up
higher, makes a pullback, yada yada. And
here's the key idea.
Prices tends to move around an average.
In trading, we call this the mean.
Sometimes price pushes far above the
average, and sometimes it could drop way
below the average. But, over time, it
tends to come back towards the middle,
come back towards the average, come back
towards the mean.
And that's mean reversion trading in a
nutshell. Prices that move too far away
from the average tends to snap back
towards the mean.
Now, you can think of it like a rubber
band. If I take a rubber band, okay, and
I stretch it, the further I pull it, the
stronger the force that wants to snap it
back to its original shape. Agree?
That's what happens with stock prices as
well.
When a stock drops too far away from the
mean, away from the average, there's a
natural force that wants to snap it back
towards the average, towards the mean.
And that's mean reversion trading in
action.
You can think of it like your wife's
mood, right, when you forgot your
wedding anniversary.
If you forget the wedding your wedding
anniversary, your wife's mood is going
to drop really fast, like a rock
plummeting from the 100th floor.
But, eventually, with enough apologies,
flowers, and sorrys, your wife's her
mood will eventually revert back towards
the mean.
So, same thing over here. And later on,
I'll share with you a mean reversion
trading system with the exact trading
rules on when exactly to buy and sell.
No guesswork required. But, first, you
need to understand why, why mean
reversion trading works. And this is
what I'm going to share with you right
now.
So, why does mean reversion trading work
even though everyone else seems to know
about this?
And the answer is simple.
At least simpler than you think.
Markets are driven by emotions like fear
and greed. Always have been, always will
be. And this is what fuel movement in
price. When prices quickly fall, when it
collapse, something interesting happens.
Traders panic, weak holders, they sell.
Stop loss get triggered. Short-term fear
spikes. And the selling feeds on itself.
One person sells, pushes the price
lower, next person sells, and then
before you know it, you have a cascade
of selling pressure, an avalanche of
selling pressure.
And this scares
the next person to sell, on and on.
So, it's like a stampede, right? When
one person runs for the exit, and
suddenly everyone else is running as
well. Even the guy who has no idea
what's happening, "Oh, let's run. I also
run."
So,
here's the thing, right? More often than
not, that selling pressure is
exaggerated. It's an overreaction.
Now, let me give you a real-world
example.
Imagine a solid company, maybe a company
like Apple, Google, etc. It has good
earnings, strong balance sheet, a
well-run management team, nothing
fundamentally wrong with it. But, one
day, the broader market gets spooked by
some economic headline. Maybe there's a
war, geopolitical tension, rise in
interest rates, whatever.
And the whole market then drops, it
collapse.
And what about this good company?
Well, the stock price drops 10% in 2
days.
Now, this
the price dropped
not because there's anything wrong with
the business, but rather it drops
because everyone else is panicking at
the same time. It's like, you know, one
kid in the classroom. When one kid
cries, the next thing you know, two kids
are crying. Before you know it, the
entire classroom
are filled with crying kids. It's like a
virus that spread.
So,
what usually happens next?
Well, the fear eventually fades.
Rational buyers step in, and they see a
stock trading at a discount for no
fundamental reason. And they buy.
And then, the price rebounds higher. So,
this is mean reversion trading in a
nutshell. You're buying the overreaction
and selling the recovery.
Now, I know you might be thinking, "But,
Rayner, what if it's not an
overreaction? What if the stock price
keeps falling? Cheap becomes cheaper?"
Good question. And this is exactly where
most traders get it wrong, right? I will
share with you what are some of the
mistakes to avoid later as a mean
reversion trader. But, for now,
understand the principle behind mean
reversion trading, which is, you know,
short-term overreactions create
opportunities for mean reversion
traders.
And now that you understand this
concept, right, you understand what is
mean reversion trading, how it works,
and why it works, I'm going to share
with you an actual mean reversion
trading system backed by 25 years of
data. So, let's get to it.
Okay, now, let me walk you through the
exact trading rules of the mean
reversion trading system.
And by the way, what I'm about to share
with you is for educational purposes
only. Don't go and trade this on a live
account the next day. Please do your
homework, do your testing, do your
backtesting. This is uh what my lawyer
made me say. Okay, I don't have a
lawyer, but if I do have a lawyer,
that's what my lawyer would want me to
say. So, please do your homework, your
testing before risking any real money.
So, for this mean reversion trading
system, we are trading stocks in the
Russell 1000 index. So, these are the
largest 1000 stocks in the US.
Time frame is a daily time frame. And
this one is important, the risk
management. It's 20% of your capital for
each stock and a maximum of five
positions. So, what this means is that,
let's say you have $10,000 trading
capital, and you want to trade this
particular system. This means that for
each stock, you will allocate not more
than $2,000 per stock.
Why $2,000? Because it's 20% of your
capital. If your capital is $10,000, 20%
is $2,000. And if you have, let's say
you long all five stocks, 2000 * 5, you
realize that you'll be $10,000, which is
your total capital. So, for this system,
there is no use of leverage. And this is
how we manage our risk and size up our
positions.
Now, moving on, let's talk about the
exact trading rules, right, the rules
that has
allowed this system to generate 2,834%
over the last 25 years.
First thing we're looking for is to make
sure that the stock is above the 200-day
moving average, because
stocks that are in an uptrend, right,
based on my research and even on
academic research, stocks that are in an
uptrend, they are the ones likely to
continue higher. So, we want to avoid
buying stocks in a downtrend. We want to
avoid buying stocks which are cheap,
because these are the
the stocks, right, which are, you know,
cheap will become cheaper. So, avoid
those stocks. And the way we do it is by
making sure the stock is above the
200-day moving average.
Next,
to define the pullback, to define the
rubber band stretch, we want to make
sure that the stock closes below the
lower Bollinger Band.
And our Bollinger Band settings is based
on 20-day moving average,
okay, and 2.5 standard deviation. The
default settings for most Bollinger
Bands across most platforms is 20-day
moving average and two standard
deviation. But, for us, we're going with
2.5 standard standard deviation, because
we want to, you know, look for the more
uh bigger stretch of the rubber band, if
you know what I mean.
So, once we have that, then the third
thing we're looking for is to place a 3%
buy limit order based on the previous
day closing price. So, how this works is
that, let's say criteria one and two is
met, and the stock price closed at $100.
So, how do we then place a 3% buy limit
order? Just take the closing price,
multiply by 0.97,
okay, and you'll get $97. This is the
buy limit order that we'll be placing
for this stock on our brokerage account.
And don't worry if
all this seems a little bit fuzzy for
you. I'll walk you through a trading
example later on later on, so you can
see how all this works on the charts.
Number four, if your order is filled,
then you sell when the two-day RSI
crosses above 50 or after 10 trading
days. So, this is our exit criteria, the
signal to tell us when to sell, to exit
our position. When the two-day RSI
crosses above 50 or after 10 trading
days.
And this is the Bollinger settings that
I mentioned earlier. So, all in all, if
you were to look at the charts, it looks
something like this. Let me just kind of
give you a nicer
screen to see. So, stock is in an
uptrend, above the 200-day moving
average, then it makes a pullback. Okay,
at this point, let's say you imagine
that there's a Bollinger Band over here.
Let me just draw it out, something like
this. The stock closes below the lower
Bollinger Band, okay?
Then we're going to place a buy limit
order somewhere over here. If the next
day the stock price continues down lower
and hits our buy limit order
we will go long buy. Okay? And when the
stock makes a bounce, okay, let's bounce
let's say bounce up high over here,
closes
okay, we're going to sell.
So, you can see that this system, right?
We're looking to
buy
near the lows of the Bollinger Band and
then sell
on the first bounce higher. So, now let
me walk you through a
chart so you can see how it looks like.
Okay, so this is the chart of Tesla and
if you recall our trading rules, first
thing is that the stock must be above
the 200-day moving average. So, if
you're on TradingView or whatever
platform you're on, just look for moving
average. I'm just going to find it for
you.
Okay, it's a simple moving average.
Click on this and we have this blue line
over here. We need to make sure that it
is
200-day moving average. I'll change it
to 200. The style, I like black for
200-day.
Okay, so you can see the stock right now
it's above the 200-day moving average as
shown over here.
Next thing if you recall is that the
stock price must close below the lower
Bollinger Band. So, go to indicators,
look for Bollinger Bands.
There we have it, Bollinger Bands. Click
on this.
And I'm going to change the settings.
The only thing you need you need to
change is again as mentioned earlier,
the default setting is usually 20 period
moving average and two standard
deviation. We're going to go with 2.5
standard deviation to widen the band to
make sure our rubber band is, you know,
stretch further.
Click okay. And there we have it. You
can see over here. Right now, this is a
the Bollinger Bands
on the chart. This is the upper
Bollinger Band, the lower Bollinger Band
and then is the moving average. So, so
we're looking for the stock price to
close below this green line over here,
which it did. So, right now at this
point
criteria one and two are met. Criteria
one is stock above the 200-day moving
average. Criteria two
the stock price closed below the lower
Bollinger Band. Criteria three now,
we're looking to place a 3% buy limit
order
based on the previous day closing price.
So, what's the previous day closing
price? So, if you just look at this, let
me
just get you a horizontal line here,
okay? I'll just change this to black is
fine.
So, the previous day closing price you
can see over here it's 401.99. So, I'm
just going to put here
401.99
which is shown by this black line over
here. And to place a a 3% buy limit
order, I just multiply this by 0.97
and it's going to give me an answer of
using my trusty calculator
389.93.
So, what I'm going to do is place a buy
limit order at 389.93.
Okay, let's just see.
389.93.
I'll change this to green to signal that
it's a buy limit order to see whether we
get filled or not the next day. And I'm
going to tell you that we are definitely
going to get filled because this is a
cherry-picked chart.
Boom, there you have it. Okay, so this
green candle, okay, you can see over
here the low of the day
was at this price point. Clearly where
we would have gotten filled on the trade
if you're using at least a decent
broker, right? Unless you're using some
weird broker that, you know, doesn't
give you good fills, otherwise you
should most likely get filled on the
trade. So, now we are in a long
position. So, now when do we then exit
the trade? So, if you recall it's when
the two-day RSI
crosses above 50 or after 10 trading
days. The 10 trading days is a
time-based stop loss because there are
times where the stock price just
collapse day after day, right? Without
any bounce at all. So, that is our
time-based stop loss to
to prevent further damage and that's the
use of our time-based stop loss. But
more often than not, usually we exit
when the two-day RSI crosses above 50.
So, right now I'm just going to get my
RSI indicator out
and to see when it closes above
when the when the two-day RSI crosses
above 50. So, the RSI length change this
to two.
You don't need the moving average, click
none.
Okay, then click okay. So, right now you
can see that the RSI value, I'm going to
show you on the charts, it's 16.27.
We're waiting for it to be above 50. So,
let's see what happens.
Okay, so right now it's 41, not yet.
Right now it's 20, not yet. Still 41,
not yet. Still 15, not yet. 9, not yet.
Boom, 84. You can see over here.
Where do I get 84? Look at this value
over here. The two-day RSI value now is
84. So, we are actually looking at this
this line at the bottom of where this
line this line that we're looking at
earlier. The value's going up and down.
So, right now it's 84 and this is a
signal to to exit our trade.
So, what we're going to do is that we
will then exit the stock at the next day
open. So, when the stock price exit over
here or rather when you open over here,
let me just
put the red line over here, open it
here.
Okay, this is where we would have exit
this position. So, you can see the green
line, our buy limit order is where we
buy
and the red line is where we sell. So,
you can see in essence this trading
system, we're looking to buy pullbacks
in an uptrend when the stock makes a
bounce, boing, we sell and then thereby
capturing like kind of like this one
swing, one move in the market.
So, what I've shared with you earlier is
a objective
trading rules, an objective trading
system where the rules
doesn't require any subjectivity,
guesswork or whatsoever. And because the
rules are objective
you can test it across the last, you
know, 10, 20 years and see how this
particular trading system has fared.
Let's find out.
So, over here is the results of this
mean reversion trading system that has
been backtested over the last 25 years.
As you can see over here, I'll just walk
you through the tables and the number.
So, this is the year in 2000, this
particular system for the year made 97%.
You can even see the breakdown on month
on month, right? In January it's up 12%,
February up 0.3%, etc.
Then in 2004, it lost 7.8%. 2024, it
made 29%. So, you can see the numbers
here for yourself. Quite
self-explanatory.
If you look at the equity curve of this
system, you can see that it has been
consistently making money over the last
25 years. So, this is the start of the
equity curve and this is the end of
2024. Making a series of higher highs
and higher lows, otherwise known as an
uptrend. And along the way we have
drawdowns along the way. It's not one
straight line or there's there's
drawdowns along the way, but had you
stick to the rules of this trading
system, you will be
out you'll be out you'll be you have
come out, you know, much ahead.
And over the last 25 years, you can see
that the
average annual return is about 14.47%,
all right? Easily beating the S&P 500
and that's not it, right? The maximum
drawdown is 24% over here.
Okay, not sure if you can see it, but
yeah, this is the
annual return, this is the maximum
drawdown and you compare to the S&P 500
I believe the S&P 500 over the last 25
years max drawdown is about 55, 60%.
You can see the winning rate of this
particular system is about 66% winning
rate, all right? Close to 70%. 66%
winning rate for this trading system.
So, all in all you can see that this is
a
trading system that has an edge in the
markets and likely to continue working,
right? Based on the the reasons I shared
with you earlier.
Now, let me share with you the three
common mistakes that traders make
when they
are trading with a mean reversion
strategy.
Mistake number one, they are buying
stocks in a downtrend. So, remember
earlier we
are only buying stocks in an uptrend,
stocks above the 200-day moving average.
But there are traders who, you know,
skip this step. They ignore the 200-day
moving average. They see a stock, you
know, drop 40, 50% from the highs and
they think to themselves "Oh man,
Rainer, this is a bargain. This is a
This is a cheap stock. It has to
bounce."
Well, it doesn't have to bounce. It
doesn't have to do anything. A stock
that's in a downtrend, it can keep
falling and falling and falling some
more. What's cheap can become cheaper.
That's not mean reversion trading.
That's a stock in a free fall.
That's a stock that's taken a one-way
ticket to the basement and it's not
coming back up for dinner.
So, mean reversion works when you're
buying temporary pullbacks in a healthy
uptrend.
The keyword here is
pullback in an uptrend.
If a stock has been in a downtrend for 6
months, 8 months or more, then
it's not a pullback in an uptrend. It is
the new reality. That is not a dip, but
rather, you know, a jump off a cliff.
The second mistake is no risk
management. So, here's the thing.
Even the best mean reversion system, it
will experience losing streaks, losing
trades. Earlier you've seen that we have
about a 33% chance
of losing.
So, the question is when you lose, how
much do you lose? If you put all your
trading capital all into one stock and
if the stock drops, you know, 50, 60%,
you can imagine that loss can be really
painful. Or if somehow the stock that
you buy
you know, is fraudulent and what more,
you could lose, you know, almost all of
your trading capital.
So, one bad trade can really, you know,
hurt you badly. But if you spread your
bets across 10 stocks, then a loss is
now a lot more manageable because the
loss is now a fraction of your capital.
You can brush it off and move on. So,
risk management it isn't sexy. Nobody
makes, you know, viral YouTube videos
about risk management, Kelly criterion,
but this is is actually what separates
traders who survive in the long run and
traders, you know, who blow up your
their accounts and then complain, "Ah,
trading is a scam." The third mistake is
trading without an edge, trading without
backtested rules.
I get it, you know, you watch a video on
YouTube by a guy called Rayner Teo, and
he talks about mean reversion trading,
and you think to yourself, "Great. I'll
just eyeball the charts, look for stocks
that are overstretched, and then buy
it."
But that's not systems trading. That is
discretionary trading
dressed up in a mean reversion costume.
And this is the reason why most traders
get inconsistent results, because
when you have backtested rules, rules
that are verifiable with
historical data, you take the emotion
out of the equation.
You're no longer relying on your gut
feel
or feelings. Instead, you're relying on
math,
proven mathematical strategies
backed by data that tells you when
exactly to buy and when exactly to sell
without guesswork. And when your actions
are consistent,
you get consistent results. Now, I want
to manage your expectations. I'm going
to be honest with you, even though this
is something that you might not want to
hear.
Mean reversion strategies, when done
properly, tend to have certain
characteristics, and you need to know
what are some of these characteristics,
right, before you start trading this
system.
First, mean reversion system tends to
have a high winning rate, anywhere
between 60 or even up to 70% winning
rate. You might have, you know, 65, 67%
winning rate. That sounds amazing,
right? Winning, you know, seven out of
10 trades.
But here's the thing, right, before you
mentally start, you know, thinking of
buying your next Lambo or renting a
penthouse or whatnot, you must also
understand that it comes with a small
profits per trade.
The profits on each trade is usually
relatively small. You're not looking to
catch massive trends. You're just
catching short-term bounce in the
market. That's what you've seen earlier.
So, your average winning trade might be,
you know, 2, 3%. Whereas your average
losing trade might be 3, 4%, which is
larger than the average size of your
winners.
This means that even though you're
winning often, you're winning a lot,
each individual win isn't going to make
you feel like a a genius. It's more like
a steady drip of a fire hose,
not glamorous. You're not going to be
posting screenshots on Instagram of the
big money that you are making, but, you
know, it works, and all this adds up
over time.
Now, let me ask you a question.
Would you prefer a strategy that wins
30% of the time,
but it has massive winners, or a
strategy that wins 70% of the time,
but with pretty small winners?
There's no right or wrong answer. It
depends on your personality. My wife
would pick the 70% winning rate, because
she likes being right about everything
all the time, especially when it
concerns about me being wrong.
Anyway, mean reversion trading system,
it falls into the second category. High
winning rate with relatively small
profits per trade.
And here's the part that nobody wants to
hear as well.
Even with a high winning rate, you will
still face losses. You will still
encounter losing streak.
Let's say your winning rate is 70%. This
means out of every 10 trades, there are
about three losers. But those three
losers, they are not spread out evenly.
Sometimes you might have five, six,
seven, eight losses in a row, and that's
perfectly normal. It's all part of the
statistics. It is not personal. The
market is not out to get you, even
though sometimes it feel like it is,
okay? And during this losing streak,
your brain might be screaming at you,
going to say, "Ah, this doesn't work
anymore. It's time to change strategy.
It's time to look for something better,
something, you know, more powerful,
Rayner."
Here's the thing. If you have backtested
your trading system, if you understand
the what and the how, and more
importantly, the why behind this trading
system, you know it has an edge over
hundreds of trades. You know that the
losing streak is just noise. This is
simply the price of admission. So, the
bottom line is this.
Mean reversion trading is not a
get-rich-quick scheme.
It's a consistent, systematic trading
approach that generates consistent
returns over time, but only
if you trust the process and follow the
rules.
Next, I want to share with you something
really important.
Professional traders,
traders who make money consistently
every year, whether it's a bull market,
a bear market, or even during a
recession, they don't just have one
system.
Here's why.
A mean reversion trading system might do
well when the market is choppy, when
it's range-bound,
but when the market's, let's say it's in
a very strong bull market without much
pullback, a mean reversion trading
system will likely be on the sidelines,
because there's no
way to enter
when the markets are trending strongly.
So, in this case, a trend-following or
momentum system will do better.
And this is why when you combine
multiple trading systems together, you
will smooth out your equity curve. Your
drawdowns are shorter, and in other
words, you sleep better at night. And
this is why
professional traders, they adopt
multiple trading systems, so they can
profit in bull and bear markets, even
during a recession.
Just to give you an example, imagine
this. You own one restaurant.
If that restaurant has a a bad, a lousy
year, then your income for the year will
collapse, agree?
By the same token, if you own five
restaurants in five different locations,
even if one restaurant doesn't do well
for that year, even if it struggles, the
other restaurants will help keep your
business
profitable overall. And it's the same,
right, with having multiple trading
systems.
So, if you want to learn multiple
trading systems, so you can smooth out
your returns over time to profit in
different market conditions, then go and
grab this free training that I've
prepared for you. The link is somewhere
below this video, or just go down to
tradingwithrayner.com/go,
right, or you can find it in the
description below.
So, this training, right, will equip you
with not one, not two, but three
different trading systems. I've shared
with you one, which is the mean
reversion trading system I shared with
you earlier. You'll also learn a
trend-following system plus a momentum
trading system. Again, I'll walk you
through the exact trading rules with
examples, so
everything is objective. Everything is
quantifiable, and you can take these
rules and test it and see whether it
works or not, because I don't want you
to take my word for it. So, along the
way, I will also provide with you
Okay, this is you can see the the
results of all these different trading
systems based on the backtest results.
I'll also give you the PDF slides of the
training,
the trading cheat sheet, plus the
backtest report of all these different
strategies. So, all this will be sent to
you for free. If you're interested, just
go down to tradingwithrayner.com/go.
You'll be brought to this page over
here. Just click on this orange button,
right, and I'll send it to your email
address. So, I'll put the link somewhere
below.
Get
access to it, and I will talk to you
soon.